In this video, we're finally going to
cover the Dirac equation in particle
physics.
We've already covered the Klein-Gordon
equation for classical scalar fields and
the Proca equation for classical vector
fields.
Now, we're going to cover the Dirac
equation for classical spinner fields,
including the concepts of spin and
chirality.
Some concepts like helicity and
antimatter, I'm going to be covering in
the next video.
The Dirac equation is more difficult
than the previous two equations because
it involves spinners and gamma matrices,
which are unfamiliar to most physics
students unless they've studied them
specifically.
I've already covered the different types
of spinners in video nine, and I've
covered some of the properties of the
gamma matrices and the Dirac equation in
video 22.
So, if you find this video hard to
understand, you can check the links in
the description to watch those videos
first.
To arrive at the Dirac equation, the
basic idea is that we take the
Klein-Gordon equation and introduce the
complex I so that we get a difference of
squares.
Then, we factor it into two pieces.
We assume that the square root of this
derivative operator is a linear
combination of the four space-time
derivatives with these gamma
coefficients.
If we square this linear combination, we
get 16 terms, which must equal the four
derivative terms in the original
Klein-Gordon equation.
Therefore, we conclude that gamma t
squares to +1, gammas x, y, and z square
to -1,
and swapping the order of two gammas
introduces a negative sign, so that the
terms in this lower triangle cancel with
the terms in this upper triangle.
Since the gammas do not commute, they
must be matrices instead of scalar
numbers.
If we take 1/2 of this factored
equation, we get the Dirac equation.
The gammas here are written as 4x4
matrices, and the field psi is written
as a four-component Dirac spinner.
Technically, we could include spinner
summation indices on these objects, but
we often leave the spinner indices out
for convenience, with the understanding
that standard array multiplication rules
will be used.
Now, I'm going to talk about the Dirac
Lagrangian density and Dirac equation
solutions in a moment, but first I want
to talk about some conventions used in
this video.
First, let's remind ourselves that there
are many possible choices for what the
gamma matrices could be.
The only requirement is that they
satisfy these properties here.
It's often convenient to write the 4x4
gamma matrices using the smaller 2x2
sigma matrices seen here.
All the sigma matrices square to the 2x2
identity matrix, and they also all
anti-commute with each other.
In video 22, I showed this matrix
solution for the gammas, which is called
the chiral basis or Weyl basis.
In the chiral basis, the top two
components of a Dirac spinner represent
the spin-up and spin-down components of
a left chiral Weyl spinner, and the
bottom two components represent the
spin-up and spin-down components of a
right chiral Weyl spinner.
Under Lorentz transformations, these
left and right spinners rotate in the
same direction, but boost in opposite
directions.
This mirror opposite behavior is why we
call them left and right chiral
spinners.
I also showed this other matrix solution
called the mass basis or Dirac basis.
Here, the x, y, z gamma matrices are the
same, but gamma t is modified.
We'll see later that we can move from
the chiral basis to the mass basis by
changing the spinner basis using this
matrix U.
When a Dirac spinner changes basis with
a matrix U like this, vectors like the
gamma matrices will change basis with U
on the left and U inverse on the right
like this.
And this change of basis gives us the
mass basis.
So, anytime I solve the Dirac equation
in this video, I'll be showing the
solutions in the chiral basis, but I'll
also show what the same solutions look
like in the mass basis.
And as I said in video 22, I do think
it's best to interpret the gammas as
space-time basis vectors, since they
each have a space-time index.
They're just a different representation
of basis vectors compared to what we're
used to, and they come with useful
algebraic relations.
Now, I'm going to point out some sign
conventions on the gammas with raised
and lowered indices.
Typically, raising or lowering an index
on one of the gammas involves using the
Minkowski metric eta.
This basically leaves gamma t alone and
flips the signs of gammas x, y, and z.
To be consistent with textbooks, I'm
writing the gammas with upper indices in
this video with the following matrix
convention for the chiral basis.
This is inconsistent with my previous
videos in this series, where I wrote the
exact same matrices, but for gamma with
lower indices.
I hope that this new convention isn't
too confusing, but I'm using it to stay
consistent with most textbooks.
Also, in previous videos, when writing
out complex waves, I haven't been very
particular about whether I used a plus
sign or a minus sign, since it didn't
matter too much in most cases.
But in this video, the sign convention
is more important, so I will be using a
negative sign in the complex waves by
default.
Again, this is what most textbooks use,
so I hope it helps avoid confusion.
Okay, so let's finally start solving the
Dirac Lagrangian and equation.
So, the Lagrangian density that produces
the Dirac equation looks like this.
There's a kinetic term involving
space-time derivatives and a mass term.
These terms involve both the field psi
and its Dirac adjoint psi bar.
The Dirac adjoint psi bar is defined as
the Hermitian conjugate of psi times
gamma t.
I showed in video 22 that this inner
product of psi bar does not change under
a Lorentz transformation.
So, we need to use this inner product in
the Lagrangian density because we want
the Dirac field to have laws of physics
that look the same after a Lorentz
transformation.
An important thing to note here is that
the Dirac equation is complex in the
sense that the components of the spinner
psi are complex numbers.
So, we can start putting this Lagrangian
through the Euler-Lagrange equations.
And recall the psi and psi bar fields
and their derivatives are treated as
independent variables.
Technically speaking, we would be taking
derivatives with respect to the
components of psi, but we're going to
leave the spinner indices out as a kind
of notation shortcut. We'll get the same
results either way.
If we use the Euler-Lagrange equations
varying with respect to psi bar, on the
left side, we can take this psi bar
derivative and distribute it to both
terms.
We simply get the derivative of psi bar
with respect to psi bar, which is one.
And we're left with this.
For the right side of the equation, the
Lagrangian has no partial psi bar terms,
so we immediately get zero.
So, plugging these results into the
Euler-Lagrange equation and factoring
out psi, we get the Dirac equation for
psi.
Now, let's go through this process
again, but varying with respect to psi.
For the left-hand side, the first term
contains no psis, and so it goes to
zero.
The second term gives us partial psi by
partial psi, which goes to one. So,
we're left with this.
For the right-hand side, the second term
has no partial psis, so it goes to zero.
And for the first term, we get a
derivative of partial alpha psi by
partial mu psi.
Again, since all the partial psi
components are independent, this always
goes to zero unless alpha and mu match,
in which case it goes to one. So, this
gives us a Kronecker delta.
And this means the only non-zero term in
the sum is when mu equals alpha, so we
get this.
Pluging these into the Euler-Lagrange
equation and rearranging, we get what's
called the adjoint Dirac equation,
defining the solutions for psi bar.
Note that the adjoint Dirac equation has
a positive mass term instead of a
negative mass term.
Also, sometimes the adjoint Dirac
equation is written with psi bar on the
left, with the implication that the
derivative operator acts leftward onto
it.
So, we see that the Dirac Lagrangian
gives us two types of Dirac equations.
One with solutions for psi and one with
solutions for psi bar.
You might think that these are the
particle and antiparticle solutions, but
it turns out that for Dirac spinners,
writing the antiparticle solution will
take a little more work.
I'll talk about these antiparticle
solutions in the next video.
Now, with the real Klein-Gordon field,
we saw that we got phi solutions.
And when we moved to the complex
Klein-Gordon field, we doubled the
number of solutions and got both phi and
phi star for particles and
antiparticles.
Similarly, the real Proca field had A
solutions. And moving to the complex
Proca field doubled the number of
solutions and gave us A and A star.
With the Dirac field, the field is
already complex, and we get psi and psi
bar solutions.
It turns out that we can find a real
version of the Dirac equation called the
Majorana equation, and this has only one
set of solutions psi. And here there's
no distinction between particles and
antiparticles.
Now, let's finally look at the solutions
of the Dirac equation, which is an
equation that describes a field of Dirac
spinners.
In the Proca equation, we saw that A was
a four-component object called a vector.
In the Dirac equation, psi is a
four-component object called a Dirac
spinner.
For the Proca equation, we found that we
could write solutions using a space-time
wave part times a constant vector part,
where the vector indicates the vector
wave's polarization.
For the Dirac equation, we're going to
see that we can write solutions using a
space-time wave part times a constant
spinner part, which indicates the
spinner wave's spin and chirality.
So, let's see why that's the case.
It's actually pretty easy to see why the
Dirac equation solutions take the form
of space-time waves.
Recall that the Dirac equation was taken
to be one factor from the Klein-Gordon
equation.
If we multiply both sides by the second
factor, then the right-hand side remains
zero,
and the two factors on the left-hand
side multiply together back into the
Klein-Gordon equation once again.
So, this is telling us that all four
components of the spinner psi must
individually solve the Klein-Gordon
equation, which we know has wave-like
solutions.
So, instead of solving for the four
components individually, we can just use
one space-time wave for all four
components and then put a constant
spinner in front. And here I've labeled
the spinner components with beta.
All that's left to do is to determine
what these betas should be in order for
us to get a valid solution to the Dirac
equation.
To begin, I'm going to work in the
chiral basis.
To solve the Dirac equation, we're going
to start with a simple case where the
wave does not depend on the spatial XYZ
components and only depends on time.
So, in other words, the entire spinner
field will have the exact same spinner
components at every location in space,
but the spinner components can change
over time.
In the chiral basis, the left spinner
components will be denoted by chi up and
chi down, and the right spinner
components will be denoted by xi up and
xi down.
And I'll sometimes use this notation
here, where a Dirac spinner is denoted
just by chi and xi
with the understanding that chi and xi
each have two components for spin up and
spin down.
So, in the chiral basis, the gamma T
matrix is a 4 by 4 matrix that looks
like this, where these fancy ones each
indicate a 2 by 2 identity matrix and
the zeros indicate a 2 by 2 zero matrix.
And for the Dirac equation, after
bringing the mass term to the other
side,
we can take this summation and remove
all terms except the time term,
since the space derivatives of the
spinner psi will all go to zero, since
there is no space dependence.
I've also multiplied both sides by
negative I to bring this I to the other
side.
Next, I'll write gamma T and the Dirac
spinner in array notation.
The gamma T matrix here has the effect
of swapping the top and bottom halves of
the Dirac spinner.
So, chi and xi swap places.
Now, looking at these columns component
by component, we get two differential
equations. One where the time derivative
of xi is proportional to chi and another
where the time derivative of chi is
proportional to xi.
So, taking the first of these equations,
we can apply another time derivative to
both sides.
And then we can sub in this formula for
the time derivative of chi.
After squaring negative I to get
negative one, we get this second-order
differential equation containing only
xi.
There are two basic solutions for xi
that solve this, which are complex
exponentials with either a positive or a
negative exponent.
If we sub this formula for xi back into
the first differential equation and take
this derivative using chain rule, we get
this equation for negative chi.
If we multiply both sides by negative
one, this plus or minus sign will become
a minus or plus sign, and this is our
solution for chi.
So, we have these solutions for xi and
chi.
However, for the Dirac spinner psi, this
only tells us the wave part of the
solution, and we still need to determine
the constant spinner in front, which
I've denoted using chi and xi without
any time dependence.
There are a few solution cases we can
find.
For case one, let's take the negative
exponential solutions.
This means we take a plus sign in front
of the chi, which means xi and chi are
exactly equal.
So, if xi is in the spin up state 1 0,
then chi is also in the spin up state 1
0.
And if xi is in the spin down state 0 1,
then chi is also in the spin down state
0 1.
Any other two-component constant spinner
can be written as a linear combination
of these two spinner states. So, these
are all the solutions for case one.
Now, for case two, we'll take the
positive exponential, which means we
take a negative sign in front of chi.
So, xi and chi have opposite signs.
This means that if xi is spin up, then
chi is negative spin up. And if xi is
spin down, then chi is negative spin
down.
So, we have four basic Dirac solutions
in total.
For the negative exponential case, we
have a spin up solution and a spin down
solution, where the signs of chi and xi
match.
We'll call these solutions U1 and U2.
And for the positive exponential case,
we have a spin up solution and a spin
down solution, where chi and xi have
opposite signs.
We'll call these solutions V1 and V2.
I'm also going to multiply each of these
solutions by a normalization factor of 1
over the square root of 2.
This ensures each spinner has a
magnitude of 1.
Also, we should note that the Dirac
equation is linear, so any linear
combination of solutions is also a
solution.
So, a general solution here is any
general linear combination of our four
basic solutions.
Now, I want to point out some
alternative notation for these complex
waves.
For a stationary particle, we know that
E equals mc squared. So, if we move this
C into the brackets, we can replace mc
squared with energy E.
Also, the Planck relation tells us that
energy is equal to the angular frequency
omega times h bar.
So, we can rewrite E over h bar as the
angular frequency omega.
Now, I'll point out that if we take the
energy operator from quantum mechanics,
which is ih bar times the time
derivative,
and apply it to our negative exponential
wave, we get an eigenvalue of positive
E.
And if we apply the energy operator to
our positive exponential wave, we get an
eigenvalue of negative E.
This fact led Paul Dirac to propose that
the U solutions were for ordinary matter
particles and the V solutions were for
an antiparticle with the exact same
properties but with negative energy.
This isn't exactly the correct
interpretation according to modern
views, but we'll come back to this idea
of antimatter later.
Also, one final comment on these
solutions, you'll notice that all basic
solutions combine both left chiral and
right chiral spinners together.
For massive Dirac particles, you will
never see an individual left chiral or
right chiral particle that's stable.
They will always come in pairs.
The only way to get an individual right
chiral particle is to combine a U and V
solution together in linear combination.
However, this isolated right chiral
particle only exists at time equals
zero.
As time moves on, we again get a
combination of left and right chiral
spinners and then later get a left
chiral spinner on its own. And then
later we return to a combination of left
and right chiral spinners.
So, this solution will oscillate between
left and right chiral particles as time
moves forward.
Now, the solution we've just found can
be thought of as a kind of stationary
wave.
On a spacetime diagram, the wave fronts
would look like this.
Oscillating over time but being the same
across space everywhere in the universe.
If we wanted to get a traveling wave
solution to the Dirac equation, we could
keep this solution and just do a Lorentz
boost in the Z direction to change our
frame of reference.
In this new frame, a line of constant
time will cut across many wave fronts.
So, the wave number Kz will be non-zero.
It might be hard to understand how a
stationary wave can become a traveling
wave due to a change in reference frame.
But remember the relativity of
simultaneity.
In one frame, two distant points may
appear to have the same wave value at
the same time.
But in another frame that's boosted
relative to the first frame, the same
two points may not have these values at
the same time anymore.
So, a traveling wave can appear.
So, in order to get Dirac solutions that
are traveling waves, let's take our
stationary wave solution and boost it in
the Z direction.
This requires two steps. First, we do a
boost on the spacetime wave portion
involving the wave vector K and
spacetime coordinates X, and then we do
a boost on the constant Dirac spinner.
Let's start with boosting the spacetime
wave part.
Recall that a Lorentz boost is just a
hyperbolic rotation.
So, to boost our basis vectors in the
plus Z direction, we use hyperbolic trig
functions with a boost angle phi as
coefficients on the ET and EZ basis
vectors.
This transformation can also be written
with the basis vectors in a row and this
transformation matrix.
Since the wave covector K has lower
indices just like the basis vectors, it
will also transform with the same
matrix.
The spacetime coordinates have upper
indices and so they are written in a
column and they transform with the
inverse matrix which has the negative of
the hyperbolic angle.
So, now we know how to transform the
components in the spacetime wave.
Now, to Lorentz boost the Dirac spinner,
we're going to have to recall from video
22 that another way to represent a
four-vector is to use a linear
combination of the gammas as basis
vectors which gives this matrix here.
And to Lorentz boost this in the Z
direction, we use a double-sided
transformation involving exponentials of
a half angle and the time Z gamma
bivector.
A Dirac spinner is an object that
Lorentz boosts with only a one-sided
exponential transformation.
In the chiral basis, the time Z bivector
is a block diagonal matrix of sigma Zs.
And this turns out to be a fully
diagonal matrix.
This is useful because the exponential
of a diagonal matrix is equal to just
taking the exponentials of the diagonal
elements.
So, we can see the four-component Dirac
spinner is boosted in the Z direction
simply by multiplying its components
with these exponentials.
Now, while this answer is correct, there
are many equivalent ways of writing this
Z boosted spinner that are used across
different sources.
So, I'm going to spend a few minutes
rewriting this answer in different ways.
First off, this exponential of a half
angle can be rewritten as the
exponential of the full angle all to the
power of 1/2.
And a 1/2 exponent is the same thing as
a square root.
And recall, just as a complex
exponential can be rewritten using
cosine and sine, a real exponential can
be rewritten using hyperbolic cosine and
hyperbolic sine.
Now, we can understand cosh and sinh
better by looking at right angle
triangles in the time Z plane in
spacetime
which obey a Minkowski Pythagoras
formula that uses a minus sign.
For example, time squared minus Z
squared equals the spacetime interval S
squared.
Also, Einstein's energy-momentum-mass
relation tells us energy squared minus
momentum squared equals mass squared.
And finally, the dispersion relation
tells us that frequency squared minus
wave number squared equals mass over H
bar all squared.
In each of these three triangle cases,
we can write cosh as adjacent over
hypotenuse and sinh as opposite over
hypotenuse.
So, since our spacetime wave is
described by a wave vector, it can be
helpful to rewrite these expressions
with hyperbolic angles using frequency
and wave number.
Or if we multiply by a factor of H bar,
we can use energy and momentum.
So, our Z boosted spinner components can
be written like this.
Now, let's look at yet another way of
writing this boost matrix. This time
looking at half angle exponentials that
include sigma Z.
Since sigma Z squares to the identity
matrix, which is like the positive
number one, we can rewrite this using
the hyperbolic Euler's formula placing
sigma Z where the complex I would
normally go.
Now, these half angle hyperbolic trig
functions obey these trig identities
here that you can look up on Wikipedia.
And these involve hyperbolic cosine of
the full angle phi.
We've already seen that we can write
cosh of phi using adjacent over
hypotenuse.
And if we write the number one as
hypotenuse over hypotenuse, we can
factor out one over the square root of
the hypotenuse in front.
For sinh of a half angle, we get a
similar formula but with a minus sign.
Also, note that because sinh can be
negative, the plus or minus sign of this
square root should have the same sign as
phi. But I'm not going to bother writing
this plus or minus sign explicitly for
the rest of the video.
We can apply this formula to the case of
the energy-momentum-mass triangle
or the frequency-wave number-mass over H
bar triangle.
So, knowing all of these hyperbolic trig
identities here, we can rewrite our Z
boosted spinner like this.
As an exercise, you can check that these
solutions satisfy the Dirac equation in
the special case where the X and Y terms
go to zero.
Now, I realize this most recent boost
formula looks pretty ugly, but it does
have an advantage.
Let's say that we pick some arbitrary
boost direction B given by a linear
combination of the gamma X, gamma Y, and
gamma Z vectors.
And let's say that this boost direction
vector B has length one.
Since we're going to be using this boost
direction vector a lot, I'm going to
rewrite the components of B using the
letter N to remind ourselves that the
vector is normalized with length one.
If we calculate the spinner boost matrix
for this direction B,
we see that we get this exact same type
of block diagonal matrix that we saw for
sigma Z.
And just as sigma Z squares to one, our
boost direction vector will also square
to one since it has length one.
So, we can use this exact same boost
formula that we saw before just with
sigma z replaced with any normalized
boost direction vector of our choice.
And this lets us boost a Dirac spinner
in an arbitrary direction.
All right, I'm going to show one more
way of writing Dirac solutions in the
chiral basis.
This matrix for boosting spinners uses
exponentials of half angles.
And we've seen that we can rewrite this
half angle as the square root of a full
angle.
And then use Euler's formula to write
the exponential using cosh and sinh.
We've also seen that given a right angle
triangle in Minkowski space, we can
write cosh as adjacent over hypotenuse.
And write sinh as opposite over
hypotenuse.
I'll use the dispersion relation
triangle and set cosh to frequency over
mass.
And write sinh as wave number over mass.
Now, since we're dealing with the full
three dimensions of space here, this
dispersion relation uses the magnitude
of the 3D wave vector given here.
Now, these NI components are part of a
normal vector of length one. And when we
multiply these by the magnitude of K, we
simply get the wave number components
KI. So, we get this expression.
And here I factored out the mass terms
in front.
I've also written the 2x2 identity
matrix as sigma T, which is a common
alternative notation.
Now, if I take the plus case here, this
is really just a summation between K's
and sigmas, which I can write like this.
For the minus case, we can use this
special notation sigma bar, where sigma
bar T is the same as sigma T, but sigma
bar for the space directions is equal to
minus sigma.
So, basically, the bar flips the spatial
directions.
With this, we can write the minus case
using a summation with sigma bar.
And as usual, we can always replace the
four-dimensional wave vector K with four
momentum P using a factor of h bar.
So, given these new formulas, we can
write this spinner boost matrix using
these square root summations
to get this boosted Dirac spinner here.
Now, this formula is compact and
correct, but these sigmas are matrices,
and it's not immediately obvious how to
calculate the square root of a matrix.
Our previous solution with this big ugly
formula actually gives the result of
this square root operation.
So, we've seen how to write boosted
spinners using exponentials, using
hyperbolic trig functions, and using
physical quantities like frequency, wave
number, and mass from a right angle
triangle in space-time.
If you like, you can try squaring the
formulas in the right column here and
confirming you get the expected values
under the square root signs in the left
column.
Okay, so we've been through a lot of
math in the chiral basis. Let's sum up
all of our results for the Dirac
equation.
First, we start with the four basic
stationary solutions here, labeled U1,
U2, V1, and V2.
Then, we can boost these solutions to a
new reference frame.
To do this, we pick any three values for
the 3D spatial parts of the wave vector
K.
And then we use the dispersion relation
to get the time component, which is the
frequency.
We can use these four components in the
space-time wave part of our Dirac
solution.
Next, we need to boost the
four-component Dirac spinner accordingly
with this boost matrix.
The boost direction N is a unit vector
that we get from normalizing the spatial
components of the 3D wave vector K.
And the boost angle phi can be obtained
from hyperbolic trig formulas in our
Minkowski triangle.
We can compactly write this boost
solution using this matrix square root
notation.
But the explicit formulas for the square
roots are given here.
And of course, every frequency wave
vector component here can be turned into
an energy momentum component using a
factor of h bar.
Now, the basic solutions I talked about
before, U1, U2, V1, V2, depend on both
space-time position and the wave vector.
However, it's common to pull out the
space-time wave part and allow the U's
and V's to just denote the constant
spinner in front of the solutions, which
depend only on the wave vector.
The most generic Dirac solution involves
summing these four solutions with their
own complex scaling constants.
And also integrating over all possible
3D wave numbers.
Again, recall that frequency omega is
already determined by the three wave
numbers and the field's mass, so we do
not integrate over it.
We can also do summations over U and V
from one to two to write things more
compactly.
And this is the most generic solution to
the Dirac equation.
So, I realize we've been through a lot
of math already, but there are even more
ways to write the solutions to the Dirac
equation. And this involves moving from
the chiral basis to the mass basis.
Thankfully, this just involves taking
the solutions we already have and
changing basis with this matrix U.
If we apply this matrix U to a Dirac
spinner, the resulting top half is just
the sum of the left and right Weyl
spinners.
And the resulting lower half is just the
difference of the left and right Weyl
spinners, where the left spinner gets
the minus sign.
And we also have this scaling factor of
1 over the square root of 2.
You can sort of think of this change of
basis as a kind of 45° rotation of
spinner components.
So, let's take our four basic stationary
wave solutions in the chiral basis and
move them to the mass basis.
For U1, the sum of the left and right
spinners gives two zero.
And the difference between left and
right simply gives a pair of zeros.
The factors of 1 over square root of 2
cancel with the two to just give a one
in the first component.
So, the U1 solution has a one in the
first component and zeros everywhere
else.
The remaining basic solutions just have
a one in the second, third, and fourth
components, respectively, and zeros
everywhere else.
So, in the mass basis, the U solutions
seem to be associated with the top half
of the spinner, and the V solutions seem
to be associated with the bottom half of
the spinner.
So far, the spinner solutions look
simpler in the mass basis.
However, we also need to take our
boosted solutions and change them to the
mass basis.
Once again, in the mass basis, the top
half is the sum of left and right
spinners.
And the bottom half is their difference
with the minus sign on the left part.
Now, for the U solutions, we know in the
stationary case that the left and right
spinners are equal. So, we can replace
all the chis with xis here.
The top half now has a sum of positive
and negative exponentials.
This equals 2 * cosh with an identity
matrix in front.
And the bottom half is a difference of
exponentials. This can be written as 2 *
sinh with the normal direction vector
matrix in front.
For the V solutions, the stationary
solutions have left and right spinners
with opposite sign.
So, we can replace the chis with
negative xis.
This gives us the same spinner as the U
solutions, but with the top and bottom
halves reversed.
Now, with both of these solutions, we
can factor out the cosh in front,
provided we divide sinh by cosh to
compensate for it.
And sinh over cosh is the definition of
tanh.
Recall these identities we found for
cosh and sinh of a half angle.
Since tanh of a half angle is just the
ratio of sinh and cosh, we can take the
ratio of these formulas.
Canceling the terms in front, we get the
square root of adjacent minus hypotenuse
over adjacent plus hypotenuse.
We can multiply both the numerator and
denominator by adjacent plus hypotenuse.
On the bottom, this gives us a squared
sum, and on top, we get a difference of
squares. Which, according to hyperbolic
trig rules, gives us opposite squared.
We can now cancel the squares and square
root to get this formula for tanh of a
half angle.
And we can get a frequency wave number
version of this formula as well as an
energy momentum version of this formula.
Going back to our formulas for the
boosted spinners in the mass basis, we
can now sub in our known formulas for
cosh and tanh of half angles.
And recall multiplying the normal vector
and I components by the magnitude of K
will just give the KI components.
We can also plug in explicitly the spin
up and spin down components to get these
solutions here.
And once again, we can convert to energy
and momentum if we use a factor of h
bar.
Now recall that the U solutions have
negative exponentials and the V
solutions have positive exponentials.
Confusingly, I've seen some sources flip
the sign on the four-wave vector K
components on the V solutions to make
the exponent negative.
And the signs on K in the spinner are
flipped as a result in this case.
So to sum everything up for the mass
basis, these are the stationary
solutions. These are the boosted
solutions written with hyperbolic trig.
And these are the boosted solutions
written with physical quantities.
So let's sum everything up.
In the previous videos, we saw the real
spin zero Klein-Gordon field has one
solution per wave vector.
And the real spin one Proca field has
three solutions per wave vector because
of the three possible polarizations.
In this video, I did not cover the real
spin one-half field, which is the
Majorana field.
But it makes sense that it would sit in
between with two solutions per wave
vector, which are the spin up and spin
down solutions.
When we complexify these fields, we
double the number of solutions.
This is why the Dirac field has four
basic solutions per wave vector.
The two basic spin up and spin down
solutions are doubled after
complexification,
and we get four basic solutions in
total.
There's a spin up U solution and a spin
up V solution, and a spin down U
solution and a spin down V solution.
The U and V solutions have space-time
wave parts that are complex conjugates
of each other.
We saw that for the Dirac field, every
solution contains both a left chiral and
right chiral Weyl spinner inside of it.
We can write stationary solutions in
either the chiral basis or the mass
basis.
And we can boost these solutions to any
arbitrary wave vector K of our choice.
Finally, to get the most generic Dirac
solution possible, we take a linear
combination of these four solutions,
each with their own scaling constants,
and then integrate over all possible
wave numbers KX, KY, and KZ.
Now there are a number of topics related
to the Dirac equation that I still need
to cover, like helicity, conserved
currents, and a proper treatment of
antimatter. And I'm going to cover those
in the next video.